<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: database | devblog of @sgt_mactavish]]></title>
  <link href="http://brain64bit.github.io/blog/categories/database/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brain64bit.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-11T00:44:45+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://brain64bit.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[@sgt_mactavish]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Problem using ActiveRecord #exists? in eager load resultset]]></title>
    <link href="http://brain64bit.github.io/blog/2015/03/20/problem-using-activerecord-findermethods-number-exists-in-eager-load-resultset/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T19:16:20+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brain64bit.github.io/blog/2015/03/20/problem-using-activerecord-findermethods-number-exists-in-eager-load-resultset</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So few weeks ago i&rsquo;ve got problem in a rails apps. New Relic reports about 500 error, where the main cause is <strong>accessing method in nil object</strong>.
Here is code snippet, causing the error :
```ruby
class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  has_many :posts, &ndash;> { order &ldquo;created_at DESC&rdquo; }</p>

<p>  def latest_title</p>

<pre><code>posts.exists? &amp;&amp; posts.first.title
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```
From the code above, user object have a method <strong>latest_title</strong> it just check if user has posts and fetch the first post&rsquo;s title.
But somehow its produce weird error when calls <strong>user.latest_title</strong>.</p>

<!-- MORE -->


<p><code>ruby
undefined title of nil:NilClass
</code>
the <strong>posts.exists?</strong> returns true but when try accessing the first post its return nil, what a ridiculous error.
Based on error trace, i found the user object is generated by eager_load query, so the query look like this :
<code>ruby
users = User.includes(:posts).order(created_at: :desc).limit(10000)
</code>
the query eager_load <strong>posts</strong> association into user object!!!. So i found the conclusion why the error happen.</p>

<ul>
<li>users resultset are eager loaded the posts association into memory.</li>
<li>for the first time the query performed there are user who dont have posts, because using eager load the posts association stored as empty collection into user object.</li>
<li>inside <strong>#latest_title</strong> method its perform checking using <strong>exists?</strong> which is surprising to me is that exists? method <strong>always check directly to database</strong>.</li>
<li>the error come when timing of resultset generated is slightly difference with operation insertion post tho user who doesn&rsquo;t have posts. The eager load &amp; insertion happen concurrently.</li>
<li>because eager load the posts association still empty collection, but when exists? performed its directly check into database which is return true.</li>
<li>so what actually happen is like <strong>[].first.title</strong> which is produce the error :)</li>
</ul>


<p>Based on that conclusion, there are 2 options. First is do the query without eager load, second is instead use <strong>exists?</strong> please use <strong>any?</strong> which is come from ruby&rsquo;s enumerable, it doesn&rsquo;t directly check the database. And now <strong>latest_title</strong> method implementation look like:
<code>ruby
posts.any? &amp;&amp; posts.first.title
</code>
Just need to be gently and careful when using eager load.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
